A Guide to the Records of the Charlottesville School Board 1869-2006
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series V Financial
  - Financial receipts 1956 December, 1 notebook pt 3 (Box-folder 47:5)
  - Financial receipts 1957 January-February, 1 notebook pt 4 (Box-folder 48:1)
  - Financial receipts 1957 February-April, 1 notebook pt 5 (Box-folder 48:2)
  - Financial receipts 1957 April-June, 1 notebook pt 6 (Box-folder 48:3)
  - Financial receipts 1957-1958, 1 notebook pt 1 (Box-folder 48:4)
  - Financial receipts 1957 July-August, 1 notebook pt 2 (Box-folder 48:5)
  - Financial receipts 1957 September-November, 1 notebook pt 3 (Box-folder 48:6)
  - Financial receipts 1957-1958 November-January, 1 notebook pt 4 (Box-folder 48:7)
  - Financial receipts 1958 January-March, 1 notebook pt 5 (Box-folder 49:1)
  - Financial receipts 1958 March-May, 1 notebook pt 6 (Box-folder 49:2)
  - Financial receipts 1958 May-June, 1 notebook pt 7 (Box-folder 49:3)
  - Financial receipts 1959 July-August, 1 notebook pt. 1 (Box-folder 49:4)
  - Financial receipts 1959 September-October, 1 notebook pt. 2 (Box-folder 49:5)
  - Financial receipts 1959 November-December, 1 notebook pt. 3 (Box-folder 49:6)
  - Financial receipts 1960 January-February, 1 notebook pt. 4 (Box-folder 50:1)
  - Financial receipts 1960 March-April, notebook pt. 5 (Box-folder 50:2)
  - Financial receipts 1960 May, 1 notebook pt. 6 (Box-folder 50:3)
  - Financial receipts 1960 June, 1 notebook pt. 7 (Box-folder 50:4)
  - Financial receipts social security security fund 1959-1960, 1 notebook pt. 8 (Box-folder 50:5)
  - Financial receipts social security security fund 1960 July-September, 1 notebook pt. 1 (Box-folder 50:6)
  - Financial receipts social security security fund 1960 October-November, 1 notebook pt. 2 (Box-folder 51:1)
  - Financial receipts social security security fund 1960 December-1961 January, 1 notebook pt. 3 (Box-folder 51:2)
  - Financial receipts social security security fund 1961 February-March, 1 notebook pt. 4 (Box-folder 51:3)
  - Financial receipts social security security fund 1961 April, 1 notebook pt. 5 (Box-folder 51:4)
  - Financial receipts social security security fund 1961 May-June, 1 notebook pt. 6 (Box-folder 51:5)
  - Financial receipts social security security fund 1960-1961, 1 notebook pt. 7 (Box-folder 51:6)
  - Financial receipts 1961 July, 1 notebook (Box-folder 52:1)
  - Financial receipts 1961 July-August, 1 notebook pt.1 of 7 (Box-folder 52:2)
  - Financial receipts 1961 September-October, 1 notebook pt.2 of 7 (Box-folder 52:3)
  - Financial receipts 1961 November-December, 1 notebook pt.3 of 7 (Box-folder 52:4)
  - Financial receipts social security fund 1961-1962, 1 notebook pt.4 of 7 (Box-folder 52:5)
  - Financial receipts 1962 January-February, 1 notebook pt.5 of 7 (Box-folder 52:6)
  - Financial receipts 1962 March-May, 1 notebook pt.6 of 7 (Box-folder 52:7)
  - Financial receipts 1962 June, 1 notebook pt.7 of 7 (Box-folder 53:1)
    includes reimbursements for principals
  - Financial receipts 1962-1963, 1 notebook (Box-folder 53:2)
  - Financial receipts (social security funds) 1962 July-September, 1 notebook (Box-folder 53:3)
  - Financial receipts (social security funds) 1962 September-October, 1 notebook (Box-folder 53:4)
  - Financial receipts (social security funds) 1962 October-December, 1 notebook (Box-folder 53:5)
  - Financial receipts (social security funds) 1963 April-May, 1 notebook pt. 1 (Box-folder 53:6)
  - Financial receipts (social security funds) 1963 February-March, 1 notebook pt. 2 (Box-folder 54:1)
  - Financial receipts (social security funds) 1963 February-March, 1 notebook pt. 3 (Box-folder 54:2)
  - Financial receipts (social security funds) 1963 February-December, 1 notebook pt. 4 (Box-folder 54:3)
  - Financial receipts 1963 July-August, 1 notebook pt.1 of 7 (Box-folder 54:4)
  - Financial receipts 1963 September-October, 1 notebook pt.2 of 7 (Box-folder 54:5)
  - Financial receipts 1963 November-December, 1 notebook pt.3 of 7 (Box-folder 54:6)
  - Financial receipts 1964 January-February, 1 notebook pt.4 of 7 (Box-folder 55:1)
  - Financial receipts 1964 March-April, 1 notebook pt.5 of 7 (Box-folder 55:2)
  - Financial receipts 1964 May-June, 1 notebook pt.6 of 7 (Box-folder 55:3)
  - Financial receipts social security funds 1963 July-October, 1 notebook pt.7 of 7 (Box-folder 55:4)
  - Financial receipts 1964, 1 notebook (Box-folder 55:5)
  - Financial receipts Activity Fund 1967 August, 1 notebook (Box-folder 55:6)
  - Financial receipts Activity Fund 1967-1968 September-April, 1 notebook (Box-folder 55:7)
  - Financial receipts Activity Fund 1968-1969, 1 notebook (Box-folder 55:8)
  - Financial receipts Activity Fund 1969-1970 August-February, 1 notebook (Box-folder 56:1)
  - Financial receipts Activity Fund 1970 February-June, 1 notebook loose pages (Box-folder 56:2)
  - Financial receipts Activity Fund 1970 May-December, 12 small notebooks (Box-folder 56:3)
  - Financial receipts Activity Fund 1970 September-December, 16 small notebooks (Box-folder 56:4)
  - Financial receipts Activity Fund 1970 September-December, 25 small notebooks (Box-folder 56:5)
  - Financial receipts Activity Fund 1970 September-December, 14 small notebooks (Box-folder 56:6)
  - Financial receipts Activity Fund 1970 September-December, 13 small notebooks (Box-folder 57:1)
  - Financial receipts Activity Fund 1970 -1971, 1 notebook and 12 small notebooks (Box-folder 57:2)
  - Financial receipts Activity Fund 1970-1971, 9 small notebooks (Box-folder 57:3)
  - Financial receipts Activity Fund 1971 January-June, 20 small notebooks (Box-folder 57:4)
  - Financial receipts Activity Fund 1971 September-December, 9 small notebooks (Box-folder 57:5)
  - Financial receipts Activity Fund 1971-1972, 3 small notebooks (Box-folder 57:6)
  - Financial receipts Activity Fund 1970-1972, 50 loose receipts (Box-folder 58:1)
  - Financial receipts Activity Fund 1970-1972, 70 loose receipts (Box-folder 58:2)
  - Financial receipts for Construction Funds and School Improvement Funds for the Local, State, Venable School, and Joint Negro High Schools. 1950, 1 notebook pt. 1 (Box-folder 59:1)
  - Financial receipts for Construction Funds and School Improvement Funds for the Local, State, Venable School, and Joint Negro High Schools. 1951-1954, 1 notebook pt. 2 (Box-folder 59:2)
  - Financial receipts School Construction Fund 1954-1956, 1 notebook pt. 1 (Box-folder 59:3)
  - Financial receipts School Improvement fund, Joint Negro High School 1954-1958, 1 notebook pt. 2 (Box-folder 59:4)
  - Financial receipts School Building Fund 1958-1962, 1 notebook pt. 3 (Box-folder 59:5)
  - Financial receipts Pupil Scholarship Fund 1960 September, 1 notebook pt 1 (Box-folder 60:1)
  - Financial receipts Pupil Scholarship Fund 1960 October, 1 notebook pt 2 (Box-folder 60:2)
  - Financial receipts Pupil Scholarship Fund 1960 November-December, 1 notebook pt 3 (Box-folder 60:3)
  - Financial receipts Pupil Scholarship Fund 1961 February, 1 notebook pt. 1 of 3 (Box-folder 60:4)
  - Financial receipts Pupil Scholarship Fund 1961 February, 1 notebook pt. 2 of 3 (Box-folder 60:5)
  - Financial receipts Pupil Scholarship Fund 1961 February & May, 1 notebook pt. 3 of 3 (Box-folder 61:1)
  - Financial receipts Pupil Scholarship Fund 1962 February, 1 notebook pt. 1 of 3 (Box-folder 61:2)
  - Financial receipts Pupil Scholarship Fund 1962 February, 1 notebook pt. 2 of 3 (Box-folder 61:3)
  - Financial receipts Pupil Scholarship Fund 1962 February & April, 1 notebook pt. 3 of 3 (Box-folder 61:4)
  - Financial receipts Pupil Scholarship Fund 1962 September-October, 1 notebook pt. 1 of 3 (Box-folder 61:5)
  - Financial receipts Pupil Scholarship Fund 1962 October, 1 notebook pt. 2 of 3 (Box-folder 61:6)
  - Financial receipts Pupil Scholarship Fund 1962 November-December, 1 notebook pt. 3 of 3 (Box-folder 62:1)
  - Financial receipts Pupil Scholarship Fund 1963 February 14, 1 notebook pt. 1 of 3 (Box-folder 62:2)
  - Financial receipts Pupil Scholarship Fund 1963 February 14, 1 notebook pt. 2 of 3 (Box-folder 62:3)
  - Financial receipts Pupil Scholarship Fund 1963 February 14, 1 notebook pt. 3 of 3 (Box-folder 62:4)
  - Financial receipts Pupil Scholarship Fund 1963 September-October, 1 notebook pt. 1 of 3 (Box-folder 62:5)
  - Financial receipts Pupil Scholarship Fund 1963 October-November, 1 notebook pt. 2 of 3 (Box-folder 63:1)
  - Financial receipts Pupil Scholarship Fund 1963 November-December, 1 notebook pt .3 of 3 (Box-folder 63:2)
  - Financial receipts Pupil Scholarship Fund 1963 August, 1 item (Box-folder 63:3)
  - Financial reconciliation of school accounts n. d., 24 items very dirty (Box-folder 63:4)
  - Financial reimbursements for travel 1963, 17 items (Box-folder 63:5)
  - Financial reports and audits 1932-1936, 5 items (Box-folder 63:6)
  - Financial reports and audits 1937-1944, 1 notebook (Box-folder 63:7)
  - Financial reports and audits 1941-1947, 14 items (remove fasteners) (Box-folder 63:8)
  - Financial reports and audits R. G. Hantzmona & Co .[1948-1962], 14 items (Box-folder 63:9)
  - Financial reports Buford cash receipts 1967 June, 1 item (Box-folder 63:10)
  - Financial Treasurer Monthly Reports 1955-1956 July-June, 1 notebook (needs flattening) (Box-folder 64:1)
  - Financial Treasurer Monthly Reports 1959-1960, 1 notebook (Box-folder 64:2)
  - Financial Monthly Report of City Treasurer to School Board 1961 July-1962 December, 1 notebook pt 1 (Box-folder 64:3)
  - Financial Monthly Report of City Treasurer to School Board 1963 January-June, 1 notebook pt 2 (Box-folder 64:4)
  - Financial statements and warrants 1909-1911, 48 items (Box-folder 64:5)
  - Financial statements and warrants 1910-1915, 25 items (Box-folder 64:6)
- Series VI: Minutes of the School Board
  Other minutes are included with the correspondence because they relate directly to various subjects in the correspondence.)
  - Minutes of the Charlottesville School Board 1879, 1 item (Box-folder 65:1)
    Photocopy from an article in the Jeffersonian Republican printing the minutes of the School Board regarding corporal punishment and teaching methods for arithmetic, grammar and other subjects.
  - Minutes of the Charlottesville School Board 1896-1898, 1 item (Box-folder 65:2)
    Bound ledger of handwritten minutes from the School Board
  - Minutes of the Charlottesville School Board 1896-1898, 43 loose pages from the bound ledger (Box-folder 65:3)
  - Minutes of the Charlottesville School Board 1904-1905, 8 items (Box-folder 65:4)
- Series VII: Newspapers
  - News clippings about school issues 1913-1915; 1933, 36 items (Box-folder 66:1)
    News clippings from The Daily Progress including articles by Superintendent James G. Johnson about the overcrowding at Midway School and plans for a new elementary school (McGuffey School).
  - News clipping about proposed school budget 1929 August 7; 1933, 2 items (Box-folder 66:2)
    There is an invitation to the public to hear the proposed school budget for the 1929-1930 school sessions and an article about Dr. James G. Johnson and the Parent Teacher Association. (The Daily Progress)
  - News clippings (Daily Progress) about school related issues 1920; 1940; 1941; 1945; 1963-1967, 24 items (Box-folder 66:3)
    Main topics include construction; student School Board; discipline; new schools and additional space; sex education; and merging of city and county resources. Articles also mention salaries of superintendents; hiring "Negro" teachers; and kindergarten programs.
  - News clippings (Daily Progress) about school related issues 1968-1971, 28 items (Box-folder 66:4)
    In addition to the main topics there are also clippings about interns; busing; library video and television studio; and overcrowding.
  - News clippings (Daily Progress) about school related issues 1972-1974, 70 items (Box-folder 66:5)
    Included with the main school topics, are articles about corporal punishment; busing; special education; naming and a move to Charlottesville High School; redistricting plans for Yancey School; exchange programs with Tandem, and Montessori schools.
  - News clippings(The Daily Progress) about school related issues 1975-1981; 1983, 84 items (Box-folder 66:6)
    Topics include budget cuts; moment of silence; retirement of the Reverend Henry B. Mitchell; election of Mayor Charles L. Barbour; racial discrimination (suspension of three "black" girls) and lawsuit; racial balance and socioeconomic tensions; competency plans; and a new gymnasium at Charlottesville High School.
  - News clippings (The Daily Progress) Mayors 1967-1978, 12 items (Box-folder 66:7)
    Mayor G. A. Vogt encouraged communication from the community; Mayor Burkett A. Rennolds, City Councilmen Bernard J. Haggerty and Lindsay B. Mount declined re-election; Mayor Mitchell Van Yahres urged constituents to voice any concerns; Mayor Charles L. Barbour charged that there were secret meetings; selection of Mayor Nancy K. O'Brien, and Laurence A. Brunton.
  - News clippings (The Daily Progress) about Superintendent William J. Ellena 1973-1975, 39 items (Box-folder 66:8)
    Also includes editorials written by Superintendent Ellena.
  - Virginius Dabney article "The Real Reasons For Cheating" 1963 May 26, 1 item (Box-folder 66:9)
  - Jack Harrison Pollack article "Should we separate smart and average kids?" and other articles. 1965- 1980, 8 items (Box-folder 66:10)
    Articles from Science and Technology; Time, Nation's Business, Parade, Phi Delta Kappan on teaching and the condition of the education system
- Series VIII: Miscellaneous: Schools, Principals, and Teachers
  - Personnel Policies [1920-1930;] 1966, 60 items (Box-folder 66:11)
    There are a list of retirements, resignations, and appointments; and minutes. There is also a list of teachers at Buford Junior High School and a news clipping about teachers being hired.
  - Principal Carrie Burnley 1931; 1942; 1954, 25 items (Box-folder 66:12)
    There are photographs and an obituary of School Principal, Carrie Burnley. There are also memos and personal writings about the proper methods for teachers, and lesson plans by Miss Burnley.
  - Programs Head Start 1964-1965, 13 items (Box-folder 66:13)
    Charter and job descriptions for the Head Start Program
  - Schools 1973-1974, 7 items (Box-folder 66:14)
    There are descriptions of Burnley-Moran, Clark, Greenbrier, Johnson, Jackson-Via, and Venable elementary schools regarding census, demographics and socioeconomic status of school neighborhoods. There is also a list of the School Board members and the principals of all the city schools.
  - Schools Jackson P. Burley Junior High School 1940-1945, 3 items (Box-folder 66:15)
    School Board minutes and planning for more space for "Negro" schools
  - Schools Charlotttesville High School 1991, 1 item (Box-folder 66:16)
    Audit report on the quality of Charlottesville High School
  - Schools Jefferson High School 1924; 1945; 1958; 1963; 2001, 21 items (Box-folder 66:17)
    There is a deed transferring the Jefferson School property to the City (January 23, 2002) as the "Carver Recreation Center;" a title search and a copy of the original deed of the Jefferson School Property (January 27, 1894 ;) and a history of Jefferson School for approval as a historic site. Included is a report about a conflict between the principal and teachers of Jefferson School.(1945)
  - Schools Lane High School 1963; 1976-1978, 13 items (Box-folder 66:18)
    There is information about the sale of Lane High School to Albemarle County for office space including the deed of sale. There is also a student's request for grades and news clippings about the sale. There are also clippings from 1963 about the overcrowding at Lane.
  - Schools McGuffey Elementary School 1912-1943, 40 items (Box-folder 66:19)
    School song; information and news clippings about William Holmes McGuffey and the "McGuffey Readers;" letter from Carrie C. Burnley to Mr. Henry Ford; letter from Dr. McGuffey's granddaughter; list of faculty at McGuffey; student certificates; and a description of the parade from Midway to the opening of McGuffey School.
  - Schools Midway School 1905-1915, 2 items (Box-folder 66:20)
    There is an essay on crowded conditions (with a list of teachers and enrollment figures) at Midway and the development of the library.
  - Schools songs and poems n. d., 12 items (Box-folder 66:21)
    There are miscellaneous songs and poems
  - Students 1919; 1941; n. d., 1 item (Box-folder 66:22)
    There is a paper on the founding fathers and their independence by a student. There is correspondence from students in Brussels, France. There is also an explanation for why a student received a zero on his examination.
  - Teacher: Hunter Haswell Walker 1979; 1992, 4 items (Box-folder 66:23)
    There are funeral programs and a news clipping about Walker's fifty years as a math teacher.
  - Teacher Lesson Plans Grammar and High School 1904-1905, 1 bound ledger (Box-folder 67:1)
  - Teacher lesson plans and invitations 1917-1940; n. d., 69 items (Box-folder 67:2)
    There are spelling lists, stories; lists of poems and values; calendars; illustrations of the University and Monticello; and history lessons. There is also a list of schools and teachers.
  - Oversize: Colored illustrations from the Ladies Home Journal of Soldiers from World War I [1919, 2 items
    The illustrations are from paintings by Gayle Porter Hoskins and Frank E. Schoonover.
  - Oversize: Black and white illustrations from Illustrated Current News1897, 2 items
    "Sight Spans Space Over Wire by Television" and "Getting Set for South Africa's Greatest Diamond Rush"
  - Oversize: Schedule of classes 1915, 1 item
  - Teacher Lesson Plans Geography n. d., 1 item (Box-folder 67:3)
    There is a typescript copy of " Guyot's Geographical Primer."
  - Teachers salaries 1916; 1942-1943, 22 items (Box-folder 67:4)
    There are letters and miscellaneous reports about salaries, summer school and tuition grants.
  - Teacher Science Department 1963-1965, 11 items (Box-folder 67:5)
  - Teacher war bonds 1942, 40 items (Box-folder 67:6)
    List of teachers and amounts deducted from salaries to pay for war bonds.
- Series IX Photographs
      - Photographs Charlottesville School Board n. d., 74 items (Box-folder 67:7)
        Included are photographs of the Reverend Henry B. Mitchell; [ ] Eberhardt; Grace Tinsley; J. A. "Buddy" Kessler; Elizabeth Bowers; Dale Metcalf; Richard Jennings; William J. Ellena; Charles Webb; Thomas McClernon; Guidance Services; Marvin Sutphin; Lane High School Band; Board meetings; Charlottesville High School; Venable Elementary School; Burnley-Moran Elementary School; Greenbrier Elementary School; Jackson-Via Elementary School; Johnson Elementary School; Buford Middle School; and Walker Middle School.
      - Photographs Charlottesville School Board n. d., 5 items (Box-folder 67:8)
        James Harry Michael, Jr., Booker T. Reaves, J. A. Kessler, Jr, Grover W. Forloines, Hovey S. Dabney, Marvin C. Sutphin, Thomas J. Michie, Jr., and Betty B. Glass.
      - Photographs McGuffey Music Festival n. d., 34 items (Box-folder 67:9)
      - Photograph construction of McGuffey Primary School 1916 March 22, 1 item (Box-folder 67:10)
      - Photograph of McGuffey Primary School by Holsinger n. d., 1 item (Box-folder 67:11)
      - Photograph 1847 A. R. McKee portrait (and one unidentified) n. d., 1 item (Box-folder 67:12)
      - Photograph Midway School 1932 February, 1 item (Box-folder 67:13)
      - Photograph construction of Venable Primary School [1924], 1 item (Box-folder 67:14)
      - Photographs of unidentified children playing n. d., 1 item (Box-folder 67:15)
      - Photographs of unidentified children in classrooms n. d., 4 items (Box-folder 67:16)
      - Photographs of Preston Avenue and Harris Road Neighborhood 1938, 7 items (Box-folder 67:17)
      - Photograph of an unidentified group n. d., 1 item (Box-folder 67:18)
      - Photographs and negatives of schools n. d., 50 items (Box-folder 67:19)
      - Oversize Photograph unidentified [site for McGuffey School] n. d., 1 item
      - Oversize Photograph of McGuffey School n. d., 1 item
- Series X Deeds, Reports and Records
  - A. Deeds
    - Deed of Gift Freedmen's Bureau 1869, 1 item (Box-folder 68:1)
      There is a deed in which the Freedmen's Bureau, [The Bureau of Refugees, Freedmen and Abandoned Lands], transferred the Delevan building. There is also an interpretation of the intended use of Delevan as a school (1893)
    - Deed of Purchase between Charlottesville School Township and City Commissioner for a parcel of land 1871 October 14, 1 item (Box-folder 68:2)
      Charlottesville School Township wanted to purchase a parcel of land located on the southern suburbs of Charlottesville (property had liens on it)
    - Deed of Purchase from Maupin Family to the Charlottesville School District 1882, 1 item (Box-folder 68:3)
      Deed for parcel of land "known as Midway"
    - Deed Contract agreement between Charlottesville City School Board and the Charlottesville District of Albemarle County 1910, 1 item (Box-folder 68:4)
      Agreement that Charlottesville City School would instruct County Students for the School Session 1910 through 1916 for a fee.
    - Opinion regarding title and property of McKee Row in which the County School Board granted use without purchase to the Charlottesville School Board 1914, 1 item (Box-folder 68:5)
      Opinion reveals the history of Charlottesville and the Courthouse and McKee property.
    - Title examination regarding John C. Patterson Property 1915 May 12, 1 item (Box-folder 68:6)
      There is a Title investigation and approval for purchase of land between Jefferson and Market Street by the Charlottesville School Board.
    - Deed of Purchase from the Patterson Family to the Charlottesville School Board and Abstracts of Title 1863-1915, 7 items (Box-folder 68:7)
      Purchase of land for McGuffey School and abstracts of titles going back to 1863. There is also some correspondence from a tenant of the Patterson Property.
    - Deed of Purchase from Bessie V. Walker to the City of Charlottesville for purchase of eleven parcels of land 1922 October 26, 1 item (Box-folder 68:8)
      Deed for land sold [through the Trader's Land Company] for thirteen hundred and seventy five dollars.
    - Resolution of the Charlottesville School Board that plats of land were trusted to the City of Charlottesville 1922 November 1, 1 item (Box-folder 68:9)
      Resolution was passed by the Charlottesville School Board for the City to be the trustee for certain property until the School Board could afford to pay for them.
    - Deed of Purchase from C. W. Allen and E. C. McCue to the City of Charlottesville 1922 November 9, 1 item (Box-folder 68:10)
      Deed is for a plat of land situated near Preston Heights and was sold [through the Trader's Land Company] for two thousand, five hundred dollars.
    - Deed of Purchase from Helen A. Woods to the City of Charlottesville 1922 November 13, 16 and March 29, 3 items (Box-folder 68:11)
      Preston Heights property (eleven parcels of land) purchased [for Venable School]. There is also a deed between Helen A. Woods and Willie Love for the purchase of certain plats in the Preston Heights property by Willie Love (lien) and a deed from Willie and Elizabeth Love to the Charlottesville School Board.
    - Deed of Purchase from John W. and Mary L. Fishburne and Lilie S. Dinwiddie to the City of Charlottesville 1922 November 17, 1 item (Box-folder 68:12)
      Deed is for a plat of land sold [through the Traders Land Company] situated on Preston Heights property for ten thousand five hundred dollars.
    - Deed of Purchase from Burruss Antrim to the City of Charlottesville 1922 November 18, 1 item (Box-folder 68:13)